hello everyone
it is june 2nd 2022
and we're in week five of textbook group
cohort one
we're having our second discussion on
chapter two
and we will uh get right to the
questions
first just wanted to highlight the math
learning group especially for those who
are
not regularly attending the meetings yet
the meetings are on 19 utc on wednesdays
but just with everything
don't let the synchronous time dissuade
you we can set up other synchronous
times if people want to co-work
and also the resources and the
modifications are all asynchronous
so we've been doing several things in
the
math learning group
first we've been sharing important
resources and categorizing them so if
somebody wants to
look at a video on something or find a
textbook on something or if you come
across something useful just add it here
and then if you feel like
leveraging the resources that you or
other people have added then you can
categorize it in the table and just add
a few pieces of information on it
we have a notation table that we'll be
building especially as we get into the
continuous time active inference
we have some questions
less so questions about the textbook and
more so just cool math questions that
people are raising as they're discussing
the material
and then we're building a math oriented
overview
so we've gotten up to equation 2.5
in chapter two
and this is just sort of like point by
point like what are the formalisms doing
where are the figures coming into play
how are some things related
and
any and all note taking can be added you
can always add it to like unsorted notes
or errata and then we can categorize it
later but this is how we develop a
shared epistemic resource that's useful
for everyone
and we're going to come to this in the
questions so we won't go into detail
right now
but
equation 2.5 is the variational free
energy 2.6 is about expected free energy
the g
and
this is a key equation instead of
equations so yesterday with um
uh blue
brock jessica jacob
we
went through
and line by line we went with examples
natural language readings
questions interpretations
and then jakob added um some
derivations like how are those three
lines in 2.5 related to each other how
do we go from the energy and entropy
formulation to the complex complexity
accuracy formulation
so
this is the essence of understanding the
equations
it's an infinite learning journey for
everyone so whatever level whether you
want to be
um
catching up to what has been written
here or whether you see ways to
reorganize it and go beyond and add more
connections
every single
background and level of math familiarity
can contribute in this way but we'll
come to the more details on 2.5 in the
questions
any
just
preliminary thoughts that people would
like to share
they can raise their hand or write in
the chat at any time
is there anything that anybody wants to
share before we start going through the
questions
starting with the most upvoted ones that
we haven't addressed
but we'll just pause for a few seconds
tune into the chapter 2 regime of
attention
upvote any questions that you'd like to
see addressed
post anything in the chat
yes jose
yeah i i'd like to ask if there's a
recording of the
math sessions which you had
no no
we record stick mergingly with the
traces in the notes but and we had this
conversation like about whether it
should be recorded or etc
if there's enough desire we could do
something like have some unrecorded and
some recorded this session is obviously
recorded and rewatchable here
and we do many live streams and there is
a lot of recorded material and so we
want to also hold a space for people who
don't want to
speak on a recorded version even though
everything's recorded in universe and in
each other's minds
but um
yes if there's enough interest in people
who want to record sessions we
absolutely will do it
we also just wanted to make sure that
there was a total
open math learning space where people
wouldn't even have that cross their
horizon
but we did discuss that yesterday
thank you
yeah any other like comments
people can just raise their hand with
six in gather or right in the chat so
we're going to um
just
go to the questions
and there's still time to upload like
during the discussions and we're just
gonna uh
i upload the ones once we've discussed
them so we'll start
with the first question that we haven't
discussed yet
okay this is from page 32.
policy dependent outcomes
are not immediately available but they
can be predicted by chaining together
two components of the generative model
the first is our beliefs about
how hidden states change their time
just want to find what the second
part was
the second component is the likelihood
distribution
what really changes as a result of
policy selection
the hidden states or the outcomes
bringing a jacket doesn't necessarily
change the temperature hidden state but
instead changes my observation
perception of whether it's cold or not
can we actually change hidden states
with policy selection and what would be
an example of this
does anyone want to raise their hand and
give a thought on
this question
what really changes as a result of
policy selection the hidden states are
the outcomes
while people are raising their hand i'll
give one possible thought
the answer is both slash it depends so
bringing a jacket does change the
temperature around you it's not just
changing your perception of temperature
so one example of changing a hidden
state with temperature
um hidden state of temperature with
policy selection would be like changing
the setting on the thermostat
that is intervening into the causal
process the generative process that's
giving rise to temperature which is
giving rise to your perceptions of
temperature
and so assuming that your temperature
perception is accurate you are able to
change both the temperature in the room
or the temperature around you with the
jacket
and
thus because temperatures are giving
rise to observations of temperature
also you end up changing both blue
so this was my question and i think um
carl kind of possibly started to answer
it on the live stream yesterday i need
to like think about it more and unpack
it a little bit more but like we don't
actually change
we change like the temperature around
ourselves but like we're not going to
change the thermometer reading by
bringing a jacket right so
there's like the
yeah
but anyway what carl said and what might
be beneficial for others to hear is that
um when you think about
what's changing it's like really when
you think about a hidden state there's a
causal chain underlying that hidden
state and the same thing like when you
think about an observation there's a
causal chain underlying that observation
so like no i'm not going to change what
my eyes tell me the temperature is but
i'm going to change what my body tells
me the temperature is and so it depends
because it's a multi-sensory
observation right so which sense is
going to change not my visual reading on
the thermometer but my physical
perception of gold
also yesterday on the live stream
thomas parr and carl first and joined so
that was really awesome and a
great one to watch 45.1 and we can
continue on this um ali and then mike
uh yeah i think that's
what meant by the word hidden
in the statement because
if
it was
transparency observation to any kind of
perception or observation
i i don't think it would it would be
called a hidden state
i believe that the reason it's called
this is it's called as such is
because it's opaque to any kind of
perception or observation
so it's kind of
inherent to the universe and uh
probably
uh not amenable to any
uh
any change or action
thanks
mike
yeah i'm not sure if i'm thinking about
it the right way but i intuitively i was
thinking that policy selection would
uh update the expected conditions or the
expected state so maybe
adjusting the priors in a bayesian
sense
so we'll come to this later but the
answer based upon the partially
observable markov decision process
discrete and continuous time versions
policies pi
intervene in between hidden states and
how they change through time
different hidden states
should they be giving rise to different
observations
will result in different observations
so changing the thermometer policy
selection is intervening in the causal
process of temperature changing through
time in the room hidden state
and if the temperature in the room is
associated through the a matrix with
your observations of temperature then
you will be changing your observations
and then just like mike said that is
reflected
based upon the expectations that the
individual has about the observations of
temperature so
they're both changing because the hidden
states and the observations are linked
that's what it means to have a
generative model
um
or for there to be a partially
observable model with hidden states and
observables
hierarchical models a given state could
be in emission from a higher state and
emitting a lower state and that's kind
of like how the current moment is like a
consequence of the past but it's a cause
of the future so this is related to
bayesian modeling but using this
architecture
we can say that policy intervenes only
in between hidden states we don't
directly intervene in how observations
appear
any other thoughts or questions on this
question
okay
all right
in figure 2.2
figure 2.2
they write
x star and x so that's going to be
generative process and generative model
latent variables hidden states do not
necessarily live in the same space of
measurement
it might be the
case that hidden states in the external
world take on values that lie outside
the space of explanations available to
the brain
conversely it might be that the brain's
explanations include variables that do
not exist in the outside world
for example the former could be
5-dimensional and the latter
two-dimensional or one could be
continuous and the other could be
categorical
so
what are examples people can think of
where the dimensionality
of the generative model
the cognitive entity
is the same as the generative process
the niche process giving rise to
observations passing them to the
generative model
that's one question
second question how does this approach
or framing
speak
to
the map territory debate
hashtag instrumentalism and realism
what papers or live streams best
characterize how active inference models
the action cognition perception loop
and what other possibilities
or models are there for the action
cognition perception loop
what would be the different strengths
and limitations of these different
framings and partitionings
thanks um joe and then blue and then
anyone else who raises their hand
so i was thinking i mean a nice case
where you could say
dimensionality is pretty obvious is uh
board games about trying to anticipate
what my opponent is going to play in a
board game
uh
you know they have a limited number of
possible moves and
i'm assuming i'm playing the same game
i'm expecting them to make some moves on
the same board so
to me that sounds like the
dimensionality of the thing
uh because you're in this like limited
world you know i don't have to know what
they're thinking i don't know if you
know what they had for breakfast i don't
have to know
a lot of stuff i'm just thinking and i
might be wrong
but moving
great thanks for that
um
so with the same dimensionality it's
like if we're playing the same game
then um we're playing a game where we're
tracking a little cursor on the screen
the movement space within that is just
the x and the y value or just two
dimensions and so
um
the observation is like
the location in two dimensions
and then
that is um the same dimensionality that
inference is occurring on
but but it's certainly i'm thinking just
to add a little bit more of my comment
if i wanted to enrich it and say oh but
you know i'm starting to think
strategically and anticipating their
next move or anticipating maybe they're
bluffing or maybe i'm bluffing and i
want to see if they know that i'm
bluffing we add more dimensionality and
i guess in principle
again you could still have that
dimensionality
in in in somehow in parity with parts of
the hidden
states you know you should i mean that
i'm thinking oh they think they know i'm
bluffing or
um
i think they're bluffing you're talking
again about the same thing you don't
have to know what they had for breakfast
you're just talking about this extra
information which isn't in the board
itself but that gets a bit more
complicated
yes
thanks
so um
that is good answer other ones that
people have written um
thermostat
is having the same dimensionality like
it's a temperature value it's a
dimensionality of one
and so then the person's
generative model
is also on this one-dimensional
temperature axis
and then they mentioned that it could be
like categorical um versus continuous
without going too many rabbit holes deep
we could just say temperature in the
room is a continuous variable it's like
taking on a number it could be a decimal
point number between
any number
zero to infinity
um
the person's model
might be the same dimensionality like
one
but then they might be trying to make a
categorical estimate is this livable or
unlivable is it hot neutral or cold
that'd be like a three-state categorical
model
so the generative process
doesn't have to have the same
dimensionality or continuous versus
discreteness of the generative
model
second answer for same dimensionality
controls for a car have two degrees
physical degrees of freedom
the acceleration the speed whether you
can hit the gas or the brake and the
direction of the front wheels controlled
by the steering wheel
so there's like a speed dimension
and then there's a turning angle
dimension
this is the model that people use when
controlling a car at some level of
abstraction
and then the acceleration dimension
can be
acted upon
through policy selections
like stepping on the gas and the brakes
and then it's like well those are two
categorically different affordances and
then there's
continuous variables inside of that
categorical difference and we'll talk
about like hybrid control models with
both
categorical and continuous aspects
in play
and in this case like the speed of the
car in the speed axis is the hidden
state
the observable would be the speedometer
so that again the gas and the brake are
policy selections that modify let's say
we're thinking about a train no turning
policy selection
is influencing
how speed changes through time
and if you have a speedometer that's
accurate
even if it's noisy it's giving rise to
observations reflecting those changes in
speed
but gas and break do not change
the speedometer directly they're
changing a hidden cause which is the
speed
different dimensionality
rain comes from clouds simple mental
models that the darker the clouds the
more they will be
that's a two-dimensional generative
model
so
how much rain
how dark the clouds
and this also is going to speak to this
map territory
some could say well there's the size of
the cloud
and there's also the humidity so that's
like maps with increasing amounts of
variables
so no one's denying the territory of the
actual chaos of the cloud
it's just a question of how much detail
and what data we're actually treating as
observables
and
what sophistication is being taken with
unobserved variables with hidden states
which are modeled
in the computer or on paper but they're
not directly observed
then the mental model can be decomposed
even more
and then
add infant item
on the reality side
the actual
generative process
for weather is
including all the butterflies
so that's
a cognitive model
that is two-dimensional in this case how
much rain is expected and how dark is
the cloud
that one could make increasingly nuanced
cognitive models
but
whatever cognitive model is being
proposed
the generative process is something
that's like totally different cognitive
model generative model map
generative process niche territory
plants do better when they have water
and fertilizer
generative mental model leaf droopiness
is a sign of moisture but leaf size and
color are signs for nutrients
so one could imagine like a causal graph
where there's like moisture level is
unobserved
but it is emitting leaf droopiness as a
state
we're observing leaf drippiness and
we're using that to infer moisture
whereas nutrient is an unobserved state
to the visual gardener
and then they're using two dimensions
leaf size and color so this is a
three-dimensional cognitive model leaf
droopiness leaf size and color are
observables
and then there's um two
unobserved cognitive states nutrients
and moisture
but whatever map gets constructed that's
not the plant now the gardener might
then want to take an informative
experiment
being an optimal bayesian gardener and
then measure something take something
that was
an unobserved in the initial model and
then measure
using lidar like using some sort of
sensor to understand and then that would
make that data point
an outcome
related
through some a matrix which we're going
to get to later
of the hidden state being like the true
levels of copper and then if we have an
accurate test we can start using the
outcomes of the observed levels of
copper and start
flushing out our model that way joe
i chucked in a comment uh below i hope
it's showing up uh
just the
other part of the question was asking
about the map territory
uh debate and and here's from the person
who kind of came up with that uh
that dichotomy in the way we we usually
talk about he says that the map and
territory should have a similar
structure and i think that's really
interesting to think about you know if
i'm making again moves in a board game
i might
you know make a reduction of their
mental state they may not maybe i'm
playing against the computer for example
so i don't know that they have a mental
state or maybe i'm playing against um
a person i happen to know as the
beginner so i know they're likely to
make naive mistakes or whatever
something like that um but i was just
thinking like with regard to the leaf
droopiness thing you could have all
kinds of really
badly badly structured uh models of
plant health
um you know like
uh maybe relate to how recently you
watered it or something that sounds good
in general but if it's a cactus
maybe that's maybe that's like a
defeater to your to your system so um
the point being like it seemed
interesting that your map should maybe
if it doesn't have exactly the same
dimensionality should still be a nice
reduction of the of the thing you're
trying to model whatever that means
thanks
one
aspect on this is
evolution natural selection dissipation
in our world sweeping off the table
entities that are failing to at least be
adequate
so
in a dissipative situation that we're in
the map has to be at least good enough
otherwise the entity will fail to exist
so that sort of closes the loop
and
is like we're seeing the persistent
entities that are acting good enough to
navigate
um and it's just interesting like how
many
from the allegory of the cave to the the
blind people and the elephant and
realism instrumentalism
and we've had many live streams
uh on this
especially check out number 14 on mel
andrews paper the math is not the
territory
so this one sort of explicitly jumps in
right there and tackles this issue with
the fep front and center so this is a
great series of live streams um the dot
zeros
are background in context where we just
go over the paper in a small group like
one person or two or three people
and then the dot one of the dot two we
usually have more of an open
participatory discussion and the authors
sometimes to usually join so everybody's
welcome to participate
in contributing to dot zeros
as well as enjoying the dot one of the
dot two but just so you know when you're
looking
in the live stream table
um the dot zero is a good one to watch
first
because it has like the background and
overview on the paper but then like
yesterday in
45.1 we had fristen and par join
to discuss just so that people can
navigate the live streams a little
better
um so we can continue
um asynchronously adding more
uh
thoughts on like map territory and what
papers and live streams and what are the
possibilities for the action perception
loop but this is these are big
fun
areas but we're going to continue with
the questions
on the notion of surprise
is the agent's
perception not only affected by the
influence
of not only its environment but also an
agent's peers
so perhaps three state is in how is an
agent's perception
affected by its direct perception and
its assessment of peers
so the agent's peers are updating their
beliefs in a collaborative fashion
what would be the extent
of the update to an agent's generative
model of perception if the agent
witnesses the annihilation of one of its
peers for example
something like this
okay
wildebeest from bird box not gonna open
any video links but perhaps we'll
observe some annihilation like some
animal attacks one of the wild beasts on
the right but then like the other one
learns
so
this is a great video definitely good to
watch
um
so far in the textbook
and indeed for the textbook it's
focusing on
just like we saw in figure 2 2 it's like
one entity
in the niche
the niche can consist of others like me
other entities that i expect are similar
to myself in terms of like the
coarse-grained cognitive architecture
they have or their preferences their
affordances they're able to do similar
things they want similar things they
have a similar history
to some extent
so
um
that is sometimes called thinking
through other minds ttom
and just to give one thought and then
anyone can raise their hand
um
if we were to accurately observe
an agent
another peer
taking some action and then failing to
exist we're driving on the highway and
then we observe somebody taking a policy
to go off the highway and then we see
them fail to exist
we could use that information
to update
our
beliefs
about the consequences of the action to
drive off the highway
so
i believe it would be possible
to
implement every variation of
direct perception direct perception of
peers thinking through other minds
theory of mind
learning by example
imitation contrarianism
every phenomena could be modeled as just
has to be
whatever the specific
um
model is actually about ali
i have a related question about
2.5 and 2.6 uh well uh correct me if i'm
wrong but uh
i understand that these equations uh
describe a kind of
uh
describe the behavior of a kind of
rational behavior the kind of behavior
of a rational agent
uh where does irrationality comes into
this um
or
let me put it this way
can irration can irrationality be a
parameter uh
in order to qualify these two equations
2.5 and 2.6 or seen
from
the other side
can we use these two equations uh to
measure the extent of rationality
as a
measurement of rationality
good question
here's one quote and we'll come to
equation 2.5 and 6 as well because those
are important
distinguishing the generative model and
the generative process is really
important
that's the difference between the entity
and the niche it's important to
distinguish them to contextualize
psychological claims about the
optimality of inference
to the extent these claims are valid on
a bayesian view is always contingent on
the organism's resource
so
don't want to step out too far but
rationy rationality and irrationality
it's rational to believe in x it is
irrational to believe in x is always
subjective from that speaker's
perspective
given the priors and the update rules
all there is is rationality which is to
say this is just the bayesian updating
process so there are maladaptive priors
ones that
trend towards dissolution of the entity
but there aren't irrational priors
there's just is what it is and how it
updates and then that could be
inadequate
um it could be any number of other
things and these are like getting into
relatively complex cognitive phenomena
um where there could be like
multiple layered models
but um
i would say
rationality in the base process is like
the cognition is bayes optimal or
modeled with a bayesian process
and then sometimes the interaction of
the generative model and the generative
process as appropriately defined
specifically
is going to result in what it results in
so if
but let's we will come to 2.5 and 2.6
but okay here suffice to say
yes
social learning and collective behavior
and emergent
uh
outcomes at the group level is something
that's important but we haven't
addressed it so far in the textbook
and multi-asian models are not really
addressed in the textbook that much
because there's so much to understand
about the kernel of the perception
cognition action loop
that
even though it's so important for real
systems
it's not brought up
okay
wanting to go to the
um equation
ah the dark room problem for many years
many papes firing back and forth
but let's go to the um equations for our
let me check the chat here yes
okay
variational free energy is minimized
through two different possible
approaches
minimizing divergence
of q and p changing mind
and maximizing evidence
taking action changing perception this
is done based upon prior and present
information
equation 2.5
variational free energy
to plan
best actions generative models and
internal policies produce simulated
outcomes that can be used to estimate
expected free energy as the average of
the log probability of outcomes
equation
2.6 expected free energy
and there's other variants
in the context of planning planning as
inference
equation 2.6 provides a view of efe that
establishes consistency in measurement
units of exploration exploitation
the relative balance between these terms
determines whether behavior is
predominantly explorative or
exploitative
34.
in other words dissolving the classic
explore exploit dilemma in behavioral
psychology
what causes this balance to change i.e
what controls this balance very
important and interesting question
perhaps we can come to equation 2.5
first and then we can come to equation
2.6
so
um where we're going
is the future
the future has several sources of in
principle and in practice uncertainty
observations in the future have not
happened
actions in the future have not happened
and the causes
of future outcomes and hidden states
actions as well as the generative
processes endogenous changes haven't
occurred so there's several like
fundamental and in practice
limitations of
the kind of precision that you can get
on the future
that's planning as inference it's
prospective
in
contrast very and that's expected free
energy because it's about the free
energy of an expected future
variational free energy f and expected
free energy is g
variational free energy f is in equation
2.5
variational free energy as the question
says
is based upon present and prior
information
so variational free energy is like
now casting
and
verging into something kind of like
memory as inference we're integrating
the past
in the sense of our priors
and the present incoming data point y
and it's like a snapshot
evaluation of optimal perception
in the purely sensory case
and if we include action within
variational free energy it's taking
one-step optimal actions
but those are not necessarily like the
ones that that's not planning that's
just like snapshot decision making
in contrast 2.6
will explicitly consider
um
policies it is a function of policy pi
and so it is including planning as
inference but first let's look at 2.5
um
jakob or anyone else
would you like to just describe
one pass
what is equation 2.5 showing
um
i guess if you mean uh like describing
say the first line or the lines in a bit
more detail
essentially it's the
um
so the
the energy term is just the expectation
of
the log of the joint probability of the
data and
the observation so i think
um
i don't understand quite why they
changed
the notation from appendix b
but
why would uh essentially be the s i
think and x would be the o
yes um anyone could be taking more notes
on this but y is the observable data
and x is the hidden state
in the pomdp that we're going to be
getting to later
x
out there the hidden state is s and o
are observations so this is using more
of a like regression
familiar like framework and variable
notation
but
this could also be written ln p of
o comma s observations and states that's
the joint distribution joint
distribution with a comma conditional
distributions with a vertical pipe
yeah and so we
also taking the the entropy term is only
based on
the beliefs of our hidden states so
for your
how
um people were saying before that the
hidden states are unobservable
the only thing that we can say about the
hidden states are the belief
cue
about the hidden states
i don't think that the
hidden states x can ever really appear
um on their own
because we always need to have some kind
of belief about them and
this was also related to a discussion we
were having yesterday
um that's interesting that they
uh used to
kind of switch between the notation of
entropy
with h
um
as the func as the functional
uh and the
and just the pure expectation uh
with the e
because the actual definition of entropy
is the expectation of the negative log
of
whatever is in
um
[Music]
is um is the variable which in this case
is q of x
uh and that's actually how we get to the
other
to the other two expressions with
complexity and accuracy and divergence
and evidence and there's also a link
i think might be wrong with uh
that to theoretical physics with
um where
free energy is essentially
the kind of cognitive statistical
equivalent of the lagrangian
which is defined as kinetic energy minus
potential energy so we were discussing
uh yesterday
what that means in terms of uh the
energy and entropy in this case whether
the energy is
perhaps
kind of the immediate um
[Music]
cognitive kinetic energy
and then the entropy
is like the potential energy or vice
versa
[Music]
might be going off on a tangent at this
point
awesome let me just add in a few other
notes
um the variables
f is a function
it's the variational free energy
function
the arguments that it is taking in
our q
that's the variational distribution that
we control that's what makes it a
variational free energy
q is the one that we control
p is the actual probability distribution
out there
y is the data point
so we have on the left side of the
equation
variational free energy is a function of
q and y
on the right side we have three equal
signs and these are three
values
three ways to phrase this one function
in the bottom here
jacob has shown how this energy minus
entropy
can result in the second line complexity
minus accuracy
and in the third line divergence minus
evidence
so that was like one really
interesting thing is it's not like this
is how it is and this is a
transformation and then this is the
transformation it
even in a sense that is also true it is
also probably helpful to think about
this
energy minus entropy formalism for what
it is
which is the closest to a physics
framing
of free energy
and then think about these two more
statistical
ontology
ways of framing it complexity minus
accuracy which is like very commonly
brought up in the context of model
fitting and divergence minus evidence
also
um
and yeah great so blue if that sounds
like a very helpful norm
in the description
we'll try to have like a description of
the equation
the first row says this this this this
this
people can type it however they want and
then of course we can replace
terms that are in the ontology
with
the special at sign
and that will facilitate
finding equations that mention those
terms
and it will facilitate translating these
equations
and
also the descriptions into different
languages computer languages and human
languages
so then we can work on it in this
ontological space
and then make sure that it's accessible
to different languages for example
um
then we thought about this example of
like
uh a ball
and its location in a bowl
so
there's a true location of where it is
in the bowl
x
and then there's an observation
of where we're observing the ball to be
so
and this also speaks to the quantum to
classical handoff
if the bowl is a swimming pool and the
ball is a bowling ball
after enough time it's going to be at
the bottom and not moving
if
the bowl is like a molecular well
and the ball is like
an electron or like one atom
then repeated measurement is going to be
entirely different and as the
ball and the ball become more massive
it approaches like a classical limit
little hints at the continuity between
classical
statistical
and quantum and thermo physics um but we
thought about this ball being in the
bowl
so
um
we looked at two different cases
which is when the ball is being observed
in the bottom of the bowl
it's like
given the generative model of the shape
of the bowl and gravity
um which is like a potential energy
function
observing the ball at the center of the
bowl is like strictly the most likely
thing that could have happened
and then observing it up on a side is
like a less likely observation
um eric and then blue
i
see uh yeah um i so it you mentioned
that uh f is a function and and as they
put it it's a function of a function
which is a functional so the way i think
about this is that
the function that it's a function of
is the q so the q is a distribution over
your beliefs
so i think of that as being a function
that you're trying to optimize you're
trying to say well how do i figure how
do i adjust my internal
belief state the q
and that's what i'm optimizing
in this equation and the functional says
that's what i'm trying to optimize is
that function and distribution and then
it breaks down into the two parts which
is
your your generative model p which says
well
um
p says for any
there's the joint probability of x
x is the the internal state
um
variable that you have a distribution
over that's q
and so how do your observables and your
internal states go together and then you
have the entropy term which is well you
want to have
maximum uncertainty so that if you're
not constrained by your observations you
want to be as agnostic as possible about
what the possible values are of your
internal states or make that q as flat
as possible
as flat as possible under the
constraints of the observations going
through your generative model p
so i guess that's the way i talk through
this this first line awesome thank you
eric blue and then brock
so eric that was super helpful um i've
been like since yesterday trying to
figure out what exactly is meant by q
here
like i get like later on we're going to
talk about q as representing beliefs but
in like as it's given as it's laid out
in chapter two like they don't actually
define q
at all
um
so i am like having a hard time up here
like they describe it
much like right before they get into
that box
they describe q in section 2.6 as an
approximate posterior
so
approximate posterior of what and like
should we
denote q as the function of beliefs here
even though
like there's it's like they're skipping
ahead and looping back at the same time
it seems like or it feels like to me
q is the variational distribution where
the form of the posterior has been
chosen
so exact base
using matrix multiplication basically or
sampling based approaches to approximate
bayesian computation like monte carlo
markov chain
those try to recapitulate the actual
form of p
so if p is truly bimodal then exact base
or sampling based approaches would try
to reconstruct that distribution
in contrast the variational approach
gains tractability because you're
choosing a posterior approximate
posterior cue
of a form that you know is going to have
a tractable optimization scheme and
there's message passing algorithms
that can do it computationally so if you
choose q to be a gaussian then
depending on how you parameterize it
it's either going to like be seeking the
mode and go to the hump that's bigger
and center around that with a variance
or it'll just spread out a lot and go
over and try to cover as much
probability density as it can by
covering both humps
okay so the variational free energy
function f as a function of the function
representing the approximate posterior q
and the data y
is equal to the negative expectation of
q given the observations x times the
natural log of the probability of the
joint distribution of the data and
observations is that the english
translation of that equation i think i
got it finally after like two days
minus close
close i would say you one one thing i
would say slightly different
it's the expectation over q not
expectation of q
we actually talked about that um a
little bit like here we had negative
expectation over q
oh and
yes
um okay
blue then yeah sorry the ontology terms
like don't match the terms that are
given in the book and i i put in a
request in the questions here if we can
append the ontology because they use
like data
is the same as like
um
observations
those are different words but there's
they're similar
like yeah there's a lot of of synonyms
or synonymous use and so like i would
hate to step on them or but like also
the terms aren't
um
in the ontology at all so maybe we
should update the ontology to reflect
the terms
we will absolutely add terms into the
supplemental or
eventually into the core terms if that's
required but just
leave a comment or email active
inference at gmail to add terms to the
ontology if there's a term that you want
to tag that's not being tagged
brock
i feel like you may have indirectly
answered this just now but um
it's in the math discussion yesterday we
were talking about
specifically about the cube the
distribution of beliefs um over the yeah
like
if x is this uncertainty term this
um
hidden state like
what
what value could it possibly have where
is it coming from
or is that
so q is this property of distribution of
beliefs is x the belief
value and that's being generated
in the previous step
i think
we in the bowl
marble thing we
like my question was uh
or i was just pointing out i guess that
you know the hidden state is changing
however it wants um perhaps below our
threshold of observation
that's not reflected in the equation for
obvious reasons and so but but then
where you know maybe it crosses a
threshold and then we update or whatever
but but where is that
x coming from if it's a hidden state
you see what i'm saying is that kind of
an ontological problem there i'm trying
to solve for it's like it's a hidden
state how can have a value or be a
variable if it's hidden
it's a
yes eric
i'll take a stab at that
so as i as shown in the pictures there's
two hidden states
there's a hidden state of the real world
and then there's a hidden state of your
generative model
and the general model is whatever the
model is and that's however the model
was built so once you have the
parameters x
then that's what you're working with
until you change your model
so that was my
habitat
yes
and over evolutionary or developmental
times
you get swept off the table if there is
inadequacy at least
but in a simulation environment you
could
make the x and x star to be anything but
um
the hidden state is as modeled by the
generative model of the cognitive entity
so
in the cognitive model of the entity in
the bowl example they're they're
modeling an unobservable which is the
location of the ball
and they're modeling an observable which
is the observation of location
so both of those are in the generative
model
and then the generative process would be
like there's somebody with a magnet
who's moving the ball around or
something or it could be anything
um
we're going to have five more minutes
before we close this session
so
what does anyone see in 2.4
what is
free energy
minimization doing
and what does it mean that variational
free energy is an upper bound on the
negative log evidence
just one quick qualitative read
is that this is what we would actually
like to be minimizing this is the floor
we truly want to reach would be
unsurprised
about observations
however
that
is intractable because we don't have
access to the form or the
parameterization of the true generative
process
what is a tractable approximation
approximate bayesian computation
is variational bayesian inference so
here's f q of y
q and y
and then this is a kl divergence
one vertical pipe means conditioned on
like x conditioned on y x given y here
probability of a hidden state being the
case given a data
or the other flipping which would be the
probability of a given data point given
a hidden state
two vertical lines is in divergence
notation
and that's the divergence between this
and that
between q of x and between p of x given
y
so
that
reducing this divergence
which has very nice properties in terms
of its
implementation
is bringing us to lower our upper bounds
on what we really want to be minimizing
in a tractable way so that's one aspect
on free energy minimization
and then um
here is reframing the two ways that free
energy variational free energy can be
minimized
through perception
the updating of beliefs and we'll talk
more about the continuity between like
perception and learning
like if one observes the ball moving
across the visual field is that
perception or is it parameter learning
updating the location of the ball that
depends on the time scale and such
or action can be taken
so that the expected observations are
changed to maximize evidence
and then
in the last minutes
ali asked
can a hidden state be an unquantifiable
quality
like a qualia quality or like an
unquantifiable quantity
no i mean uh well
of course most qualities can be
parameterized but
well
perhaps
we can think of a hidden state as a
pure quality
that cannot be
is fundamentally unquantifiable and
can we we cannot parameterize it i mean
can we think of such a hidden state
um
brock
i was just going to say the probably the
quantifiable way to state that question
is like are there
intractable
hidden states which the answer to that
is like obviously
yes
can we get some estimate on it yes
but then is that
commensurate with the i you know and
then does that mean it's a quality and
not a quantity i don't know
and also to the earlier discussion about
like the dimensionality of the
generative model and the generative
process the unquantifiable part could be
like the baby's happiness
but then
we're able to still have an inference on
the happiness as a parameter
x the underlying state that's giving
rise to the different sounds
without
necessarily knowing like the
distributional form of happiness but we
have to have a distributional form for
the variational approximation of
happiness joe
i was just going to say i mean i think
that this
qualitative versus quantitative
distinction is interesting if you're
thinking about like a light source you
know it's a source of electrons well you
could count the number of electrons but
whether or not there is a light source
they're a source of electrons
in this framework and i'm proposing
you're not counting that you're just
saying there is a light source or some
other dimension the thing we've been
calling dimensions you know yes you can
count the number of dimensions
but given that they're all different
they're not really relatable to each
other
thanks yes very interesting um so
in our final seconds
we'll just point towards 2.6
which is
expected free energy
g
and its prospective which is going to
enable
inference
conditioned on action
x hidden states the world
conditioned on policy selection
and that is what is going to allow
comparison of different policies which
are sequences of actions over a given
time horizon
so minimizing the divergence
between two things minus some things
reframing it as a few things so
we didn't go as much into 2.6 as we did
into 2.5 because 2.5 is an important
precursor and simpler cousin of 2.6
but it's like super important and we
especially to those who are here and
those who are not here we would
really love over multiple cohorts when
everybody will hopefully be able to join
and rejoin as participant as facilitator
um
to be able to annotate all the equations
with what they mean
because what is there to be said about
expected free energy
without some understanding
of what this is actually discussing what
variables go in what is it doing how are
some of them being related so
we want to learn this and we can do it
collaboratively if people just
pick and choose affordances they see
annotate some things
and then they can highlight it and say
i'm not sure about this but i just
wanted to add it can somebody improve it
and so on like we're all there to help
each other learn and improve our
epistemic niche
2.6 is expected free energy
there's further discussion
on expected free energy
showing how it's composed of these five
sections
and that by like leaving some out
you get
different special cases
that are quite important
for example leaving out this you get
this
leaving out just one you get two three
four five and so on figure two six
and then there's a summary of the low
road to active inference that's chapter
two
so this concludes chapter two and our
discussion in cohort one
in the coming two weeks we're going to
be discussing chapter three the high
road to active inference
it's going to take another attack
and we will go through it in the coming
two weeks and be addressing people's
questions but hopefully we can continue
answering and addressing just wherever
we see fit no one's gonna do it all but
we do need everybody to do some
hopefully
we're going to now close recording we'll
then take a one minute break and then in
this room we're going to continue with
dot tools
if you want to continue discussing the
textbook or anything else then head up
to a room
up and to the left but in this room in
one minute we're going to continue with
dot tools so thanks everybody see you
soon